<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!-- One method to get references from the online citation libraries.
     There has to be one entity for each item to be referenced. 
     An alternate method (rfc include) is described in the references. -->

<!ENTITY RFC1995 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1995.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3552 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3552.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4033 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4033.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4034 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4034.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4035 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4035.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5155 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5155.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5936 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5936.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6781 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6781.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8198 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8198.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis.xml">
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs), 
     please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that most I-Ds might want to use.
     (Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space 
     (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-huque-dnsop-multi-provider-dnssec-02" ipr="trust200902">
  <!-- category values: std, bcp, info, exp, and historic
     ipr values: full3667, noModification3667, noDerivatives3667
     you can add the attributes updates="NNNN" and obsoletes="NNNN" 
     they will automatically be output with "(if approved)" -->

  <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

  <front>
    <title abbrev="Multi Provider DNSSEC models">Multi Provider DNSSEC models</title>

    <author fullname="Shumon Huque" initials="S." surname="Huque">
      <organization>Salesforce</organization>
      <address>
        <email>shuque@gmail.com</email>
        <!-- uri and facsimile elements may also be added -->
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Pallavi Aras" initials="P." surname="Aras">
      <organization>Salesforce</organization>
      <address>
        <email>paras@salesforce.com</email>
        <!-- uri and facsimile elements may also be added -->
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="John Dickinson" initials="J." surname="Dickinson">
      <organization>Sinodun</organization>
      <address>
        <email>jad@sinodun.com</email>
        <!-- uri and facsimile elements may also be added -->
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Jan Vcelak" initials="J." surname="Vcelak">
      <organization>NS1</organization>
      <address>
        <email>jvcelak@ns1.com</email>
        <!-- uri and facsimile elements may also be added -->
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="March" year="2018" />

    <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->

    <area>General</area>
    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>
    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>
    <keyword>DNSSEC</keyword>
    <keyword>Multiple</keyword>
    <keyword>Provider</keyword>
    <keyword>Models</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>
        Many enterprises today employ the service of multiple
        DNS providers to distribute their authoritative DNS
        service. Deploying DNSSEC in such an environment can
        have some challenges depending on the configuration and
        feature set in use. This document will present several
        deployment models that may be suitable.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>


  <middle>


    <section title="Introduction and Motivation">
      <t>
        RFC EDITOR: PLEASE REMOVE THE FOLLOWING PARAGRAPH BEFORE
        PUBLISHING: The source for this draft is maintained in GitHub
        at: https://github.com/shuque/multi-provider-dnssec
      </t>
      <t>
        Many enterprises today employ the service of multiple
        DNS providers to distribute their authoritative DNS
        service. Two providers are fairly typical and this allows
        the DNS service to survive a complete failure of any
        single provider. This document outlines some possible
        models of DNSSEC <xref target="RFC4033" />
        <xref target="RFC4034" /> <xref target="RFC4035" />
        deployment in such an environment.
      </t>
    </section>


    <section title="Deployment Models" anchor="models">

      <t>
      The two main models discussed are (1) where the zone owner
      runs a master signing server and essentially treats the managed
      DNS providers as secondary servers, the "Serve Only" model, and
      (2) where the managed DNS providers each act like primary
      servers, signing data received from the zone owner and serving
      it out to DNS queriers, the "Sign and Serve" model. Inline
      signing and hybrid models are also briefly mentioned. A large
      part of this document discusses the Sign and Serve models, which
      present novel challenges.
      </t>

      <section title="Serve Only model" anchor="serve-only">
        <t>
        The most straightforward deployment model is one in which the
        zone owner runs a primary master DNS server, and manages the
        signing of zone data. The master server uses DNS zone transfer
        mechanisms (AXFR/IXFR) <xref target="RFC5936"/> <xref target="RFC1995"/>
        to distribute the signed zone to multiple DNS providers.
        </t>
        <t>
        This is also arguably the most secure model because the
        zone owner holds the private signing keys. The managed DNS
        providers cannot serve bogus data (either maliciously or
        because of compromise of their systems) without detection by
        validating resolvers.
        </t>
        <t>
        One notable limitation of this model is that it may not work
        with DNS authoritative server configurations that use certain
        non-standardized DNS features. Some of these features like
        DNS based Global Server Load Balancing (GSLB), dynamic
        failover pools, etc. rely on querier specific responses,
        or responses based on real-time state examination, and so,
        the answer and corresponding signature has to be determined
        at the authoritative server being queried, at the time
        of the query, or both. (If all possible answer sets for these
        features are known in advance, it would be possible to
        pre-compute these answer sets and signatures, but the DNS
        zone transfer protocol cannot be used to distinguish or transfer
        such data sets, or the rules used to select among the possible
        answers.)
        </t>
      </section>


      <section title="Sign and Serve model" anchor="sign-and-serve">

        <t>
        In this category of models, multiple providers each independently
        sign and serve the same zone. The zone owner typically uses
        provider-specific APIs to update zone content at each of the
        providers, and relies on the provider to perform signing of
        the data. A key requirement here is to manage the contents of
        the DNSKEY and DS RRset in such a way that validating resolvers
        always have a viable path to authenticate the DNSSEC signature
        chain no matter which provider they query and obtain responses
        from.
        </t>

        <t>
        These models can support DNSSEC even for the non-standard 
        features mentioned previously, if the DNS providers have the
        capability of signing the response data generated by those
        features. Since these responses are often generated dynamically
        at query time, one method is for the provider to perform
        online signing (also known as on-the-fly signing). However,
        another possible approach is to pre-compute all the possible
        response sets and associated signatures and then algorithmically
        determine at query time which response set needs to be returned.
        </t>

        <t>
        In the first two of these models, the function of coordinating
        the DNSKEY or DS RRset does not involve the providers communicating
        directly with each other, which they are unlikely to do since they
        typically have a contractual relationship only with the zone owner.
        </t>

        <t>
        The following descriptions consider the case of two DNS 
        providers, but the model is generalizable to any number.
        </t>

        <section title="Model 1: Common KSK, Unique ZSK per provider" anchor="ss-model1">
        <t>
        <list style="symbols">
        <t>Zone owner holds the KSK, manages the DS record, and is
           responsible for signing the DNSKEY RRset and distributing
           the signed DNSKEY RRset to the providers.</t>
        <t>Each provider has their own ZSK which is used to sign data.</t>
        <t>Providers have an API that owner uses to query the ZSK
           public key, and insert a combined DNSKEY RRset that includes 
           both ZSKs and the KSK, signed by the KSK.</t>
        <t>Key rollovers need coordinated participation of the zone
           owner to update the DNSKEY RRset (for KSK or ZSK), and the
           DS RRset (for KSK).</t>
        </list>
        </t>
        </section>

        <section title="Model 2: Unique KSK and ZSK per provider" anchor="ss-model2">
        <t>
        <list style="symbols">
        <t>Each provider has their own KSK and ZSK.</t>
        <t>Each provider offers an API that the Zone Owner uses to import
           the ZSK of the other provider into their DNSKEY RRset.</t>
        <t>DNSKEY RRset is signed independently by each provider using
           their own KSK.</t>
        <t>Zone Owner manages the DS RRset that includes both KSKs.</t>
        <t>Key rollovers need coordinated participation of the zone
           owner to update the DS RRset (for KSK), and the DNSKEY
           RRset (for ZSK).</t>
        </list>
        </t>
        </section>

        <section title="Model 3: Shared KSK/ZSK Signing Keys" anchor="ss-model3">
        <t>
        Other possible models could involve the KSK and/or ZSK signing
        keys shared across providers. Preliminary discussion with several
        providers has revealed that this is not a model they are comfortable
        with, again because they want to be independently responsible for
        securing the signing keys without involvement of other parties
        they don't have contractual relationships with. A possible way to
        mitigate this concern might be for the zone owner to operate a
        networked Hardware Security Module (HSM) which houses the shared
        signing keys and performs the signing operations. The signing
        instructions and results are communicated over a secure network
        channel between the provider and HSM. This could work, but may
        also pose performance bottlenecks, particularly for providers
        that perform on-the-fly signing. Due to open questions about the
        operational viability of this model, it is not discussed further.
        </t>
        </section>


      </section>

      <section title="Inline Signing model" anchor="inline-signing">
        <t>
        In this model, the zone owner runs a master server but does
        not perform zone signing, instead pushing out the zone (typically
        via zone transfer mechanisms) to multiple providers, and relying
        on those providers to sign the zone data before serving them out. 
        This model has to address the same set of requirements as the
        Sign-and-Serve model regarding managing the DNSKEY and DS RRsets.
        However, assuming standardized zone transfers mechanisms are
        being used to push out the zone to the providers, it likely also
        has the limitation that non-standardized DNS features cannot be
        supported or signed. This model is not discussed further.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Hybrid model" anchor="hybrid-model">
        <t>
        In the hybrid model, the zone owner uses one provider as
        the primary, operating in Sign and Serve mode. The other providers
        operate in Serve Only mode, i.e., they are configured as secondary
        servers, obtaining the signed zone from the primary provider using
        the DNS zone transfer protocol. This model suffers from the same
        limitations as the Serve-Only model. It additionally requires the
        signing keys to be held by the primary provider.
        </t>
      </section>

    </section>


    <section title="Signing Algorithm Considerations" anchor="algorithms">

      <t>
        In the Serve Only and Hybrid models, one entity (the Zone Owner
        in the former, and the primary provider in the latter) performs
        the signing and hence chooses the signing algorithm to be deployed.
        The more interesting case is the <xref target="sign-and-serve">
        Sign and Serve model</xref>, where multiple providers independently
        sign zone data.
      </t>
      <t>
        Ideally, the providers should be using a common signing
        algorithm (and common keysizes for algorithms that support
        variable key sizes). This ensures that the multiple providers
        have identical security postures and no provider is more
        vulnerable to cryptanalytic attack than the others.
      </t>
      <t>
        It may however be possible to deploy a configuration where
        different providers use different signing algorithms. The
        main impediment is that current DNSSEC specifications require
        that if there are multiple algorithms in the DNSKEY RRset, then
        RRsets in the zone need to be signed with at least one DNSKEY of
        each algorithm, as described in <xref target="RFC4035">RFC 4035</xref>,
        Section 2.2. However <xref target="RFC6781">RFC 6781</xref>,
        Section 4.1.4, also describes both a conservative and liberal
        interpretation of this requirement. When validating DNS resolvers
        follow the liberal approach, they do not expect that zone RRsets
        are signed by every signing algorithm in the DNSKEY RRset, and
        responses with single algorithm signatures can be validated
        corectly assuming a valid chain of trust exists. [TODO: investigate
        resolver implementations to see what they actually do.]
      </t>

    </section>

    <section title="Authenticated Denial Considerations" anchor="nsec">
      <t>
        Authentiated denial of existence enables a resolver to validate that
        a record does not exist. For this purpose, an authoritative server
        presents in a response to the resolver special NSEC (Section 3.1.3 of
        <xref target="RFC4035" />) or NSEC3 (Section 7.2 of <xref
        target="RFC5155" />) records. The NSEC3 method enhances NSEC by
        providing opt-out for signing insecure delegations and also adds
        limited protection against zone enumeration attacks.
      </t>

      <t>
        An authoritative server response carrying records for authenticated
        denial is always self-contained and the receiving resolver doesn't
        need to send additional queries to complete the denial proof data.
        For this reason, no rollover is needed when switching between NSEC
        and NSEC3 for a signed zone.
      </t>

      <t>
        The self-containment of authenticated denial responses implies that
        NSEC and NSEC3 can be used simultanously by different providers to
        serve the same zone. Doing so however defeats protection for zone
        enumeration contributed by NSEC3 and may have negative impact on how
        effectively resolvers are able to cache the responses.
      </t>

      <section title="Single Method">
        <t>
          Usually, the NSEC and NSEC3 methods are used exclusively (i.e. the
          methods are not used at the same time by different servers). This
          configuration is prefered because the behavior is well-defined and
          it's closest to the current operational practice.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Mixing Methods">
        <t>
          Compliant resolvers should be able to serve zones when different
          authoritative servers for the same zone respond with different
          authentiated denial methods because this is normally observed when
          NSEC and NSEC3 are being switched or when NSEC3PARAM is updated.
        </t>

        <t>
          Resolver software may be however designed to handle a single
          transition between two authenticated denial configurations more
          optimally than permanent setup with mixed authenticated denial
          methods. This could make caching on the resolver side less
          efficient and the authoritative servers may observe higher number
          of queries. This aspect should be considered especially in context
          of <xref target="RFC8198" >Aggresive Use of DNSSEC-Validated
          Cache</xref>.
        </t>
        <t>
          In case all providers cannot be configured for a matching
          authentiated denial, it is advised to find lowest number of
          possible configurations possible across all used providers.
        </t>

        <t>
          Note that NSEC3 configuration on all providers with different NSEC3PARAM
          values is considered a mixed setup.
        </t>
      </section>

      <!--
        Current implementations of Aggressive NSEC work with NSEC only.
        Knot Resolver plans to store "last two configrations" to handle rollovers.
      -->

    </section>

    <section title="Validating Resolver Behavior" anchor="resolver">

      <t>

	From the point of view of the Validating Resolver, the
        <xref target="sign-and-serve">Sign and Serve models</xref>,
        that employ multiple providers signing the same zone data with
        distinct keys, are the most interesting. In these models, for
        each provider, the Zone Signing Keys of the other providers are
        imported into the DNSKEY RRset and the DNSKEY RRset is re-signed.
        If this is not done, the following situation can arise (assuming
        two providers A and B):

        <list style="symbols">
        <t>The validating resolver follows a referral (delegation) to the
        zone in question.</t>
        <t>It retrieves the zone's DNSKEY RRset from one of provider
        A's nameservers.</t>
        <t>At some point in time, the resolver attempts to resolve a
        name in the zone, while the DNSKEY RRset received from provider A
        is still viable in its cache.</t>
        <t>It queries one of provider B's nameservers to resolve the
        name, and obtains a response that is signed by provider B's
        ZSK, which it cannot authenticate because this ZSK is not present
        in its cached DNSKEY RRset for the zone that it received from
        provider A.</t>
        <t>The resolver will not accept this response. It may still
        be able to ultimately authenticate the name by querying other
        nameservers for the zone until it elicits a response from one
        of provider A's nameservers. But it has incurred the penalty
        of additional roundtrips with other nameservers, with the
        corresponding latency and processing costs. The exact number
        of additional roundtrips depends on details of the resolver's
        nameserver selection algorithm and the number of nameservers
        configured at provider B.</t>
        <t>It may also be the case that a resolver is unable to
        provide an authenticated response because it gave up after
        a certain number of retries or a certain amount of delay. Or
        that downstream clients of the resolver that originated the
        query timed out waiting for a response.
        </t>
        </list>

        Zone owners will want to deploy a DNS service that responds
        as efficiently as possible with validatable answers only, and
        hence it is important that the DNSKEY RRset at each provider is
        maintained with the active ZSKs of all participating providers.
        This ensures that resolvers can validate a response no matter
        which provider's nameservers it came from.
      </t>

      <t>
        Details of how the DNSKEY RRset itself is validated differs.
        In <xref target="ss-model1">Sign and Serve model 1</xref>,
        one unique KSK managed by the Zone Owner signs an identical
        DNSKEY RRset deployed at each provider, and the signed DS
        record in the parent zone refers to this KSK. In
        <xref target="ss-model2">Sign and Serve model 2</xref>, each
        provider has a distinct KSK and signs the DNSKEY RRset with it.
        The Zone Owner deploys a DS RRset at the parent zone that
        contains multiple DS records, each referring to a distinct
        provider's KSK. Hence it does not matter which provider's
        nameservers the resolver obtains the DNSKEY RRset from, the
        signed DS record in each model can authenticate the associated
        KSK.
      </t>

    </section>

    <section title="Key Rollover Considerations" anchor="keyrollover">

      <t>
	     Key rollover for Key Signing Key(KSK) and Zone signing(ZSK) in
       multi-provider mode would require information exchange between providers(or on 
       behlaf of providers). The information needed to be exchanged for Key Signing Key 
       and Zone signing key would differ based on the sign and serve model.
      </t>
      <section title="Model 1: Common KSK, Unique ZSK per provider" anchor="krc-model1">
        <t>
        <list style="symbols">
        <t>KSK Roll: In this model the two providers share a common KSK 
          and the rollover of KSK would be handled by the zone owner. 
          The DNSKEY RRset would be resigned with the new KSK and handed 
          to the two providers to be published. The zone owner will update the DS 
          RRset in the parent zone.
        </t>
        <t>ZSK Roll: The ZSK roll for provider A would start with provider 
          A getting their new DNSKEY RRset signed by the zone owner(who holds the KSK) 
          and publishing it. The new ZSK would be added to the DNSKEY RRset of 
          provider B and signed.  
        </t>
        </list>
        </t>
        </section>

        <section title="Model 2: Unique KSK and ZSK per provider" anchor="krc-model2">
        <t>
        <list style="symbols">
        <t>KSK Roll: In this model each provider will have their own KSK. A KSK 
          roll for provider A does not require any change in DNSKEY RRset of provider 
          B. The KSK roll would start with Provider A signing their DNSKEY RRset 
          with the new KSK and sending the new KSK to the zone owner so the DS RRset 
          can be updated in the parent zone.
        </t>
        <t>ZSK Roll: In this model, ZSK roll for provider A would start with them signing 
          their new DNSKEY RRset. The new ZSK would handed to provider B to be included 
          in their DNSKEY RRset and signed.
        </t>
        </list>
        </t>
        </section>
         <t>
      Another consideration would be Pre and Post publish timing for ZSK rollover. T
      hese timings would be dependent on TTL of the DNSKEY RRset and the zone records. 
      </t>
    </section>


    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document includes no request to IANA.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>
	[TBD]
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgments">
      <t>
        This document benefited from discussions with and
        review from Duane Wessels.
      </t>
    </section>

  </middle>


  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &RFC1995;
      &RFC4033;
      &RFC4034;
      &RFC4035;
      &RFC5155;
      &RFC5936;
      &RFC8198;
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      &RFC6781;
      &RFC3552;
    </references>
  </back>

</rfc>
